<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for the uniformity of publick prayers and administration of sacraments and other rites and ceremonies and for establishing the form of making, ordaining and consecrating bishops, priests and deacons in the Church of England.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29994</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11230511</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11230511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46974</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37590)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46974)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1440:56)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for the uniformity of publick prayers and administration of sacraments and other rites and ceremonies and for establishing the form of making, ordaining and consecrating bishops, priests and deacons in the Church of England.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London by His Majesties printers and reprinted at Edinburgh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Law and legislation.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46974:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46974:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Anno XIV. CAROLI II. REGIS. AN ACT FOR THE UNIFORMITY OF Publick PRAYERS and Adminiſtration of SACRAMENTS, and other Rites and Ceremonies: And for eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the form of Making, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>London</hi> by His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Printers, and Re-printed at
<hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ANNO DOM. 1662.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46974:2"/>
            <head>Anno decimo quarto CAROLI II. REGIS. An Act for the Uniformity of Publick Prayers and Adminiſtration of Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies: And for eſtabliſhing the form of Making, Ordaining and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons in the Church of
<hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas in the firſt year of the late Queen
<hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> there was one Vniform Order of Common Service and Prayer, and of the Adminiſtration of Sacraments, Rites and Ceremonies in the Church of <hi>England</hi> (agreeable to the Word of God and uſage of the Primitive Church) compiled by the Reverend Biſhops and Clergy, ſet forth in one Book, Entituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer, and Adminiſtration of Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies in the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               </hi> and enjoyned to be uſed by Act of Parliament, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the ſaid firſt year of the ſaid late Queen, Entituled, <hi>An Act for the Uniformity of Common Prayer and Service in the Church, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments,</hi> very comfortable to all good people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to live in Chriſtian converſation, and moſt profitable to the Eſtate of this Realm, upon the which the Mercy, Favour and Bleſſing of Almighty God is in no wiſe o readily and plentifully powred, as by Common Prayers, due uſing of the Sacraments, and often Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, with devotion of the Hearers: And yet this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a great number of people in divers parts of this Realm, following their own ſenſuallty, and living without knowledge and due fear of God, do wilfully and ſchiſmatically abſtain and refuſe to come to their Pariſh-Churches, and other publick places where Common Prayer, Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and Preaching of the Word of God is uſed upon the Sundayes, and other dayes Ordained<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46974:3"/>and Appointed to be kept and obſerved as Holy dayes. And whereas by the great and ſcandalous neglect of Miniſters in uſing the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Liturgy ſo ſet forth and enjoyned as aforeſaid, great miſchiefs and inconveniencies, during the times of the late unhappy troubles, have ariſen and grown; and many people have been led into Factions and Schiſms, to the great decay and ſcandal of the Reformed Religion of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> and to the hazard of many ſouls. For pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention whereof in time to come, for ſetling the peace of the Church, and for allaying the preſent diſtempers which the indiſpoſition of the time hath contracted: The Kings <hi>Majeſty</hi> (according to His Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the five and twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty) granted His Commiſſion under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> to ſeveral Biſhops and other Divines, to re-view the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, and to prepare ſuch Alterations and Additions as they thought fit to offer; And afterwards the Convocations of both the Provinces of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> being by His <hi>Majeſty</hi> called and aſſembled (and now ſitting) His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath been pleaſed to Authorize and require the Preſidents of the ſaid Convocations, and other the Biſhops and Clergy of the ſame, to re-view the ſaid Book of Common Prayer, and the Book of the Form and manner of the Making and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons; And that after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſideration, they ſhould make ſuch Additions and Alterations in the ſaid Books reſpectively, as to them ſhould ſeem meet and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient; And ſhould exhibit and preſent the ſame to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for his further allowance, or confirmation; ſince which time, upon full and mature deliberation, they the ſaid Preſidents, Biſhops, and Clergy of both Provinces, have accordingly re-viewed the ſaid Books, and have made ſome Alterations which they think fit to be inſerted to the ſame; and ſome Additional Prayers to the ſaid Book of Common Prayer, to be uſed upon proper and emergent occaſions; And have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited and preſented the ſame unto His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in writing, in one Book, Entituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church, according to the uſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> together with the Pſalter, or Pſalms of David, Pointed as they are to be ſung or ſaid in Churches; and the Form and Manner of Making, Ordaining, and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons,:</hi> All which His <hi>Majeſty</hi> having duely conſidered, hath fully approved and allowed the ſame; and recommended to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament, that the ſaid Books of Common Prayer, and of the Form of Ordination and Conſecration of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, with the Alterations and Additions which have been ſo made and preſented to His <hi>Majeſty</hi> by the ſaid Convocations, be the Book which ſhall be appointed to be uſed by all that Officiate in all Cathedral and Collegiate Churches and Chappels, and in all Chappels of Colledges and Halls in both the Vniverſities, and the Colledges of
<hi>Eaton</hi> and<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46974:3"/>
               <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and in all Pariſh-Churches and Chappels within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and by all that Make, or Conſecrate Biſhops, Prieſts or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, in any of the ſaid places, under ſuch Sanctions and Penalties as the Houſes of Parliament ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>Now in regard that nothing conduceth more to the ſetling of the Peace of this Nation (which is deſired of all good men) nor to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Religion, and the propagation thereof, then an Vniverſal agreement in the Publique Worſhip of Almighty God; and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that every perſon within this Realm, may certainly know the rule to which he is to conform in Publique Worſhip, and Adminiſtration of Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the manner how, and by whom Biſhops, Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons are, and ought to be Made, Ordained and Conſecrated, Be it Enacted by the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, by the advice, and with the conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and of the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame, That all and ſingular Miniſters, in any Cathedral, Collegiate, or Pariſh-Church or Chappel, or other place of Publique Worſhip with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of
<hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> ſhall be bound to ſay and uſe the Morning Prayer, Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayer, Celebration and Adminiſtration of both the Sacraments, and all other the Publique and Common Prayer, in ſuch order and form as is mentioned in the ſaid Book, annexed and joyned to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Act, and Entituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer, and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the uſe of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> together with the Pſalter or Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> Pointed as they are to be ſung or ſaid in Churches; and the form or manner of Making, Ordaining, and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons:</hi> And that the Morning and Evening Prayers therein contained, ſhall, upon every Lords day, and upon all other days and occaſions, and at the times therein appointed, be openly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly read by all and every Miniſter or Curate, in every Church, Chappel, or other place of Publique Worſhip within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and places aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And to the end that Vniformity in the publique Worſhip of God (which is ſo much deſired) may be ſpeedily effected, Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that every Perſon, Vicar, or other Miniſter whatſoever, who now hath and enjoyeth any Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical benefice, or promotion within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> or places aforeſaid, ſhall in the Church, Chappel, or place of Publique Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip belonging to his ſaid benefice or promotion, upon ſome Lords day before the feaſt of Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord God, One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and two, openly, publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſolemnly read the Morning and Evening Prayer appointed<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46974:4"/>to be read by, and according to, the ſaid Book of Common Prayer at the times thereby appointed, and after ſuch reading thereof ſhall openly and publickly before the Congregation there aſſembled, declare his unfeigned aſſent, and conſent, to the uſe of all things in the ſaid Book contained and preſcribed, in theſe words, and no other.</p>
            <q>I <hi>A. B.</hi> Do here declare my unfeigned aſſent, and conſent to all, and every thing contained, and preſcribed in, and by the Book intituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites, and Ceremonies of the Church,</hi> according to the uſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Pſalter, or Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> Pointed as they are to be ſung, or ſaid in Churches; and the form, or manner of making, ordaining, and conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons.</q>
            <p>And that all and every ſuch perſon, who ſhall (without ſome lawfull impediment to be allowed and approved of by the Ordinary of the place) neglect or refuſe to do the ſame within the time aforeſaid, (or in caſe of ſuch impediment) within one Moneth after ſuch impediment removed, ſhall <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> be deprived of all his Spiritual Promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; And that from thenceforth it ſhall be lawfull to, and for all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and Donors of all and ſingular the ſaids Spiritual Promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or of any of them, according to their reſpective Rights, and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, to preſent, or collate to the ſame, as though the perſon, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo offending, or neglecting, were dead.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who ſhall hereafter be preſented, or collated, or put into any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical benefice, or promotion within this Realm of
<hi>England</hi> and places aforeſaid, ſhall in the Church, Chappel, or place of publick worſhip, belonging to his ſaid benefice, or promotion, within two Moneths next after that he ſhall be in the actuall poſſeſſion of the ſaid Eccleſiaſtical benefice, or promotion, upon ſome Lords day openly, publickly, and ſolemnly, Read the Morning and Evening Prayers, appointed to be Read by, and according to, the ſaid Book of Common Prayer, at the times thereby appointed, and after ſuch Reading thereof, ſhall openly, and publickly, before the Congregation there aſſembled, declare his unfeigned aſſent, and conſent to the uſe of all things therein contained and preſcribed, according to the form before appointed. And that all and every ſuch perſon, who ſhall (without ſome lawfull impediment to be allowed, and approved by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the place) neglect or refuſe to do the ſame within the time aforeſaid; (or in caſe of ſuch impediment within one moneth after ſuch impediment removed) ſhall
<hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> be deprived of all his ſaid Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical benefices and promotions; And that from thenceforth it ſhall and may be lawfull to, and for all Patrons, and Donors of all and ſingular the ſaid Eccleſiaſtical benefices and promotions, or any<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46974:4"/>of them (according to their reſpective Rights and Titles) to preſent, or collate to the ſame, as though the perſon or perſons ſo offending, or neglecting, were dead.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that in all places where the proper incumbent of any Parſonage, or Vicarage, or benefice with Cure, doth reſide on his living, and keep a Curate, the incumbent himſelf in perſon (not having ſome lawfull impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be allowed by the Ordinary of the place) ſhall once (at the leaſt) in every moneth openly, and publickly Read the Common-prayers and Service, in and by the ſaid Book preſcribed, and (if there be occaſion) Adminiſter each of the Sacraments, and other Rites of the Church, in the Pariſh Church, or Chappel, of, or belonging to the ſame Parſonage, Vicarage, or benefice, in ſuch order, manner, and form, as in and by the ſaid Book is appointed, upon pain to forfeit the ſum of five pounds to the uſe of the poor of the Pariſh for every offence upon conviction by confeſſion, or proof of two credible Witneſſes upon Oath, before two Iuſtices of the Peace of the County, City, or Town-Corporate where the offence ſhall be committed, (which Oath the ſaid Iuſtices are hereby impowred to Adminiſter) and in default of payment within ten dayes, to be levied by diſtreſſe, and ſale of the goods and Chattles of the offender, by the warrant of the ſaid Iuſtices by the Church-wardens, or Over-ſeers of the Poor of the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, rendring the ſurpluſage to the party.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that every Dean, Canon, and Prebendary of every Cathedral, or Collegiate Church, and all Maſters, and other Heads, Fellows, Chaplains, and Tutors of, or in any Colledge, Hall, Houſe of Learning, or Hoſpital, and every Publick Profeſſor, and Reader in either of the Vniverſities, and in every Colledge elſe where, and every Parſon, Vicare, Curate, Lecturer, and every other perſon in holy Orders, and every School-maſter keeping any publick, or private Schoole, and every perſon inſtructing, or teaching any youth in any Houſe, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Family as a Tutor, or School-maſter, who upon the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord God, One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty two, or at any time thereafter ſhall be incumbent, or have poſſeſſion of any Deanry, Canonry, Prebend, Maſter-ſhip, Head-ſhip, Fellow-ſhip, Profeſſors place, or Readers place, Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, Vicarage, or any other Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, or Promotion, or of any Curates place, Lecture, or School; or ſhall inſtruct or teach any youth as Tutor, or School-maſter, ſhall before the Feaſt-day of Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord, One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred ſixty two, or at or before his, or their reſpective ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to be incumbent, or have poſſeſſion aforeſaid, ſubſcribe the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration or Acknowledgment following,
<hi>Scilicet,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:46974:5"/>I <hi>A. B.</hi> Do declare that it is not lawfull upon any pretence whatſoever to take Arms againſt the King, and that I do abhor that traiterous Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of taking Arms by His Authority againſt His Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſionated by Him; And that I will conform to the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed: And I do declare that I do hold there lies no obligation upon me, or on any other perſon from the Oath commonly called the <hi>Solemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> to endeavour any change or alteration of Governement, either in Church, or State; And that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawfull Oath, and Impoſed upon the Subjects of this Realm againſt the known Laws, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of this Kingdom.</q>
            <p>Which ſaid Declaration and Acknowledgement ſhall be Subſcribed by every of the ſaid Maſters, and other Heads, Fellows, Chaplains, and Tutors of, or in any Colledge, Hall, or Houſe of Learning, and by every publick Profeſſor and Reader in either of the Vniverſities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Vice-Chancellor of the reſpective Vniverſities for the time being, or his Deputy; And the ſaid Declaration or Acknowledgment, ſhall be Subſcribed before the reſpective Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the Dioceſſe, by every other perſon hereby injoyned to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the ſame, upon pain that all and every of the perſons aforeſaid falling in ſuch Subſcription, ſhall loſe and forfeit ſuch reſpective Deanry, Canonry, Prebend, Maſterſhip, Headſhip, Fellowſhip, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors place, Readers place, Parſonage, Vicarage, Eccleſiaſticall Dignity, or Promotion, Curates place, Lecture, and School, and ſhall be utterly diſabled, and <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> deprived of the ſame; And that every ſuch reſpective Deanry, Canonry, Prebend, Maſterſhip, Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Fellowſhip, Profeſſors place, Readers place, Parſonage, Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Eccleſiaſticall Dignity, or Promotion, Curates place, Lecture and School ſhall be void, as if ſuch perſon ſo failing were naturally dead.</p>
            <p>And if any School-maſter, or other perſon Inſtructing, or Teaching Youth in any private Houſe, or Family, as a Tutor, or School-maſter, ſhall Inſtruct, or Teach any Youth as a Tutor, or School-maſter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Licence obtained from his reſpective Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the Dioceſſe, according to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, (for which he ſhal pay twelve-pence only) and before ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, and acknowledgment made as aforeſaid; Then every ſuch School-maſter, and other, Inſtructing and Teaching as aforeſaid, ſhall for the firſt offence ſuffer three moneths Impriſonment without bail, or mainpriſe, and for every ſecond, and other ſuch offence, ſhall ſuffer three moneths Impriſonment without bail or mainpriſe, and alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> the ſum of five pounds; And after ſuch ſubſcription made, every ſuch Parſon, Vicar, Curate, and Lecturer, ſhall procure a Certificate under the Hand and Seal of the reſpective Archbiſhop,<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46974:5"/>Biſhop, or Ordinary of the Dioceſſe, (who are hereby enjoyned and required upon demand, to make and deliver the ſame) and ſhall pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and openly Read the ſame, together with the Declaration, or Acknowledgment aforeſaid, upon ſome Lords day within three moneths then next following, in his Pariſh Church where he is to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiate, in the preſence of the Congregation there aſſembled, in the time of Divine Service; upon pain that every perſon failing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhall loſe ſuch Parſonage, Vicarage, or Benefice, Curates place, or Lecturers place reſpectively, and ſhall be utterly diſabled, and <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> deprived of the ſame; And that the ſaid Parſonage, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carage, or Benefice, Curates place, or Lecturers place ſhall be void as if he was naturally dead.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes that from and after the twenty fifth day of
<hi>March</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord God, One thouſand ſix hundred eighty two, there ſhall be omitted in the ſaid Declaration, or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment ſo to be Subſcribed and Read, theſe words following,
<hi>Scilicet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>ANd I do declare that I do hold there lies no Obligation on me, or on any other perſon from the Oath, commonly called the <hi>Solemne League and Covenant,</hi> to endeavour any change, or alteration of Government either in Church or State, and that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawfull Oath and impoſed upon the Subjects of this Realm againſt the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom.</q>
            <p>So as none of the perſons aforeſaid, ſhall from thenceforth be at all obliged to Subſcribe, or Read that part of the ſaid Declaration, or Acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, and be it Enacted that from and after the Feaſt of Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and two, no perſon, who now is incumbent, and in poſſeſſion of any Parſonage, Vicarage, or Benefice, and who is not already in Holy Orders by Epiſcopal Ordination, or ſhall not before the ſaid feaſt-day of Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> be Ordained Prieſt or Deacon, according to the form of Epiſcopal Ordination, ſhall have, hold, or enjoy the ſaid Parſonage, Vicarage, Benefice with Cure, or other Eccleſiaſtical Promotion within this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon
<hi>Tweed;</hi> But ſhall be utterly diſabled, and <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> deprived of the ſame; And all his Eccleſiaſtical Promotions ſhall be void, as if he was naturally dead.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever, ſhall thenceforth be capable to be admitted to any Parſonage, Vicarage, Benefice, or other Eccleſiaſtical Promotion or Dignity whatſoever, nor ſhall preſume to Conſecrate and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46974:6"/>the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper, before ſuch time as he ſhall be ordained Prieſt, according to the form, and manner in and by the ſaid Book preſcribed, unleſſe he have formerly been made Prieſt by Epiſcopal Ordination, upon pain to forfeit for every offence, the ſum of One hundred pounds; One moyety thereof to the Kings <hi>Majeſty,</hi> the other moyety thereof to be equally divided between the poor of the Pariſh where the offence ſhall be committed, and ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or perſons as ſhall ſue for the ſame by Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint, or Information in any of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Courts of Record, wherein no Eſſoign, Protection, or Wager of Law ſhall be allowed; And to be diſabled from taking, or being admitted into the order of Prieſt, by the ſpace of one whole year then next following.</p>
            <p>Provided that the penalties in this Act ſhall not extend to the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiners or Aliens of the Forrein Reformed Churches allowed, or to be allowed by the Kings <hi>Majeſty,</hi> His Heirs and Succeſſors in
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, that no title to confer, or preſent by lapſe, ſhall accrue by any avoidance, or deprivation <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> by vertue of this Statute, but after ſix moneths after notice of ſuch voidance, or depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation given by the Ordinary to the Patron, or ſuch ſentence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation openly and publickly Read in the Pariſh Church of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, Parſonage, or Vicarage, becoming void, or whereof the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent ſhall be deprived by vertue of this Act.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that no Form, or Order of Common Prayers, Adminiſtration of Sacraments, Rites or Ceremonies, ſhall be openly uſed in any Church, Chappel, or other publick place of, or in any Colledge, or Hall in either of the Vniverſities, the Colledges of <hi>Weſtminſter, Wincheſter,</hi> or <hi>Eaton,</hi> or any of them, other then what is perſcribed, and appointed to be uſed in and by the ſaid Book; And that the preſent Governour, or Head of every Colledge, and Hall in the ſaid Vniverſities, and of the ſaid Colledges of
<hi>Weſtminſter, Wincheſter,</hi> and <hi>Eaton,</hi> within on moneth after the feaſt of Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and two; And every Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Head of any of the ſaid Colledges, or Halls hereafter to be elected, or appointed within one moneth next after his Election, or Collation, and Admiſſion into the ſame Government, or Headſhip, ſhall openly and publickly in the Church, Chappel, or other publick place of the ſame Colledge, or Hall, and in the preſence of the fellows and Scholars of the ſame, or the greater part of them, then Reſident, Subſcribe unto the Nine and thirty Articles of Religion, mentioned in the Statute made in the thirteenth year of the Reign of the late Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and unto the ſaid Book, and declare his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned aſſent, and conſent unto, and approbation of the ſaid Articles, and of the ſame Book, and to the uſe of all the<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46974:6"/>Prayers, Rites, and Ceremonies, Forms and Orders in the ſaid Book preſcribed, and contained according to the form aforeſaid; And that all ſuch Governours or Heads of the ſaid Colledges and Halls, or any of them as are or ſhall be in Holy Orders, ſhall once (at leaſt) in every quarter of the year (not having a lawfull impediment) openly and publickly read the morning Prayer and Service, in, and by the ſaid Book appointed to be read in the Church, Chappel, or other publick place of the ſame Colledge or Hall, upon pain to loſe and be ſuſpended of, and from all the Benefits and Profits belonging to the ſame Government or Headſhip, by the ſpace of ſix moneths by the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor or Viſitors of the ſame Colledge or Hall; And if any Governour, or Head of any Colledge or Hall, ſuſpended for not ſubſcribing unto the ſaid Articles and Book, or for not reading of the morning Prayer and Service as aforeſaid, ſhall not, at or before the end of ſix moneths next after ſuch ſuſpenſion, ſubſcribe unto the ſaid Articles and Book, and declare his conſent thereunto as aforeſaid, or read the morning Prayer and Service as aforeſaid, then ſuch Government or Headſhip ſhall be <hi>(ipſo facto)</hi> void.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, that it ſhall and may be lawfull to uſe the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening Prayer, and all other Prayers and Service pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in and by the ſaid Book, in the Chappels or other publick places of the reſpective Colledges and Halls in both the Vniverſities, in the Colledges of <hi>Weſtminſter, Wincheſter</hi> and <hi>Eaton,</hi> and in the Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Clergies of either Province in Latine, any thing in this Act contained to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that no perſon ſhall be, or be received as a Lecturer, or permitted, ſuffered, or allowed to Preach as a Lecturer, or to Preach, or Read any Sermon or Lecture in any Church, Chappel, or other place of Publick worſhip, within this Realm of
<hi>England,</hi> or the Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of
<hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> unleſſe he be firſt approved, and thereunto Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Archbiſhop of the Province, or Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or (in caſe the See be void) by the Guardian of the Spiritualties, under his Seal, and ſhall in the preſence of the ſame Archbiſhop, or Biſhop, or Guardian, Read the Nine and thirty Articles of Religion, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Statute of the Thirteenth year of the late Queen
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with declaration of his unfeigned aſſent to the ſame; And that every perſon, and perſons who now is, or hereafter ſhall be Licenſed, Aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Appointed, or Received as a Lecturer, to Preach upon any day of the week in any Church, Chappel, or place of Publick worſhip within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> or places aforeſaid, the firſt time he Preacheth (before his Sermon) ſhall openly, publickly, and ſolemnly Read the Common Prayers, and Service in, and by the ſaid Book appointed to be read for that time of the day, and then, and there publickly and openly declare his aſſent unto, and approbation of the ſaid Book, and<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46974:7"/>to the uſe of all the Prayers, Rites and Ceremonies, Forms and Orders therein contained, and preſcribed, according to the form before appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this Act; And alſo ſhall upon the firſt Lecture-day of every moneth afterwards, ſo long as he continues Lecturer, or Preacher there, at the place appointed for his ſaid Lecture or Sermon, before his ſaid Lecture or Sermon, openly, publickly, and ſolemnly Read the Common Prayers and Service in, and by the ſaid Book appointed to be read for that time of the day, at which the ſaid Lecture or Sermon is to be Preached, and after ſuch Reading thereof, ſhall openly, and publickly, before the Congregation there aſſembled declare his unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aſſent, and conſent unto, and approbation of the ſaid Book, and to the uſe of all the Prayers, Rites and Ceremonies, Forms and Orders therein contained and preſcribed, according to the form afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; And that all and every ſuch perſon and perſons who ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, or refuſe to do the ſame, ſhall from thenceforth be diſabled to Preach the ſaid, or any other Lecture or Sermon in the ſaid, or any other Church, Chappel, or place of Publick worſhip, untill ſuch time as he, and they ſhall openly, publickly, and ſolemnly Read the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers, and Service appointed by the ſaid Book, and Conform in all points to the things therein appointed and preſcribed, according to the purport, true intent and meaning of this Act.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, That if the ſaid Sermon, or Lecture be to be Preached or Read in any Cathedral, or Collegiate Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, it ſhall be ſufficient for the ſaid Lecturer openly at the time afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to declare his aſſent and conſent to all things contained in the ſaid Book, according to the form aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon who is by this Act diſabled to Preach any Lecture, or Sermon, ſhall during the time that he ſhall continue and remain ſo diſabled, Preach any Sermon, or Lecture; That then for every ſuch offence the perſon, and perſons ſo offending, ſhall ſuffer Three moneths Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in the Common-Goal without bail or mainpriſe, And that any two Iuſtices of the Peace of any County of this Kingdom and places aforeſaid, and the Mayor or other chief Magiſtrate of any City, or Town Corporate, within the ſame upon Certificate from the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of the place made to him, or them of the offence committed, ſhall, and are hereby required to commit the perſon, or perſons ſo offending to the Goal of the ſame County, City, or Town Corporate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, and be it further Enacted by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, That at all and every time, and times, when any Sermon, or Lecture is to be Preached, the Common Prayers, and Service, in, and by the ſaid Book appointed to be Read for that time of the day, ſhall be openly, publickly, and ſolemnly Read by ſome Prieſt, or Deacon, in the Church, Chappel, or place of Publick worſhip, where the ſaid Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <pb facs="tcp:46974:7"/>or Lecture is to be Preached, before ſuch Sermon, or Lecture be Preached; And that the Lecturer then to Preach ſhall be preſent at the Reading thereof.</p>
            <p>Provided nevertheleſſe, that this Act ſhall not extend to the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity Churches, in the Vniverſities of this Realm, or either of them, when or at ſuch times as any Sermon or Lecture is Preached or Read in the ſaid Churches, or any of them, for, or as the publick Vniverſity Sermon, or Lecture; but that the ſame Sermons and Lectures may be Preached or Read in ſuch ſort and manner as the ſame have been heretofore Preached or Read; this Act, or any thing herein contained to the contrary thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that the ſeveral good Laws, and Statutes of this Realm, which have been formerly made, and are now in force for the Vniformity of Prayer and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments, within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and places aforeſaid, ſhall ſtand in full force and ſtrength to all intents and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whatſoever, for the eſtabliſhing and confirming of the ſaid Book Intituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer and Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church,</hi> according to the uſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> together with the Pſalter, or Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> Pointed as they are to be ſung or ſaid in Churches, and the form or manner of Making, Ordaining, and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons herein before mentioned to be joyned and annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this Act; and ſhall be applied, practiſed, and put in u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of all offences contrary to the ſaid Laws, with relation to the Book aforeſaid, and no other.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That in all thoſe Prayers, Letanies, and Collects, which do any way relate to the King, Queen, or Royal Progeny, the Names be altered, and changed from time to time, and fitted to the preſent occaſion, according to the direction of lawfull Authority.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, And be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, that a true Printed Copy of the ſaid Book, Entituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites, and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church,</hi> according to the uſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Pſalter, or Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> Pointed as they are to be ſung or ſaid in Churches, and the form and manner of Making, Ordayning and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, ſhall at the coſts and charges of the pariſhoners of every Pariſh-Church and Chappelry, Cathedral Church, Colledge, and Hall, be attained and gotten before the Feaſt-day of St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and two, upon pain of forfeiture of three pounds by the moneth, for ſo long time as they ſhall then after be unprovided thereof, by every Pariſh, or Chappelry, Cathedral Church, Colledge, and Hall, making default therein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:46974:8"/>Provided alwayes, And be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That the Biſhops of <hi>Hereford,</hi> St. <hi>Davies, Aſaph, Bangor,</hi> and <hi>Landaff,</hi> and their Succeſſors ſhall take ſuch order among themſelves, for the ſouls health of the Flocks committed to their Charge within <hi>Wales,</hi> That the Book hereunto annexed be truly and exactly Tranſlated into the <hi>Brittiſh,</hi> or <hi>Welſh</hi> Tongue, and that the ſame ſo Tranſlated and being by them, or any three of them at the leaſt viewed, peruſed, and allowed, be Imprinted to ſuch number at leaſt, ſo that one of the ſaid Books ſo tranſlated and Imprinted, may be had for every Cathedral, Collegiate, and Pariſh Church, and Chappel of Eaſe, in the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Dioceſſes and places in <hi>Wales,</hi> where the Welſh is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken or uſed before the Firſt day of
<hi>May,</hi> One thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixty five; And that from and after the Imprinting and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid Book ſo Tranſlated, the whole Divine Service ſhall be uſed and ſaid by the Miniſters and Curates throughout all <hi>Wales</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid Dioceſſes where the <hi>Welſh</hi> Tongue is commonly uſed, in the <hi>Brittiſh,</hi> or
<hi>Welſh</hi> Tongue, in ſuch manner and form as is preſcribed according to the Book hereunto annexed to be uſed in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, differing nothing in any Order, or Form from the ſaid <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Book, for which Book, ſo tranſlated and Imprinted, the Church-wardens of every the ſaid Pariſhes ſhall pay out of the Pariſh-mony in their hands for the uſe of the reſpective Churches, and be allowed the ſame on their accompt; And that the ſaid Biſhops and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, or any three of them at the leaſt, ſhall ſet and appoint the price, for which the ſaid Book ſhall be ſold; and one other Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer in the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, ſhall be bought and had in every Church throughout
<hi>Wales,</hi> in which the Book of Common Prayer in <hi>Welſh</hi> is to be had, by force of this Act, before the Firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and four, and the ſame Book to remain in ſuch convenient places, within the ſaid Churches, that ſuch as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them may reſort at all convenient times, to read and peruſe the ſame, and alſo ſuch as do not underſtand the ſaid Language, may by conferring both Tongues together the ſooner attain to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Engliſh Tongue, Any thing in this Act to the contrary notwithſtanding, and untill Printed Copies of the ſaid Book ſo to be Tranſlated, may be had and provided, The Form of Common Prayer eſtabliſhed by Parliament, before the making of this Act, ſhall be uſed as formerly in ſuch parts of
<hi>Wales,</hi> where the Engliſh Tongue is not commonly underſtood.</p>
            <p>And to the end, that the true and perfect Copies of this Act, and the ſaid Book hereunto annexed, may be ſafely kept and perpetually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and for the avoiding of all diſputes for the time to come; Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That the reſpective Deans and Chapters of every Cathedral or Collegiate Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> ſhall at their proper coaſts and charges, before
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46974:8"/>the twenty fifth day of <hi>December,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred ſixty two, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> a true and perfect printed Copy of this Act, and of the ſaid Book annexed hereunto, to be by the ſaid Deans and Chapters and their Succeſſors kept and preſerved in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for ever, and to be alſo produced and ſhewed forth in any Court of Record, as often as they ſhall be thereunto lawfully required; And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there ſhall be delivered true and perfect Copies of this Act, and of the ſame Book into the reſpective Courts at
<hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and into the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> to be kept and preſerved for ever among the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the ſaid Courts, and the Records of the Tower, to be alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and ſhewed forth in any Court, as need ſhall require; which ſaid Books ſo to be exemplified under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> ſhall be examined by ſuch perſons as the Kings
<hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhall appoint under the great Seal of <hi>England</hi> for that purpoſe, and ſhal be compared with the Original Book hereunto annexed, and ſhall have power to correct and amend in writing, any error committed by the Printer in the printing of the ſame Book, or of any thing therein contained, and ſhall certifie in writing under their Hands and Seals, or the Hands and Seals of any three of them at the end of the ſame Book, that they have examined and compared the ſame Book, and find it to be a true and perfect Copy; which ſaid Books, and every one of them ſo exemplified under the great Seal of <hi>England</hi> as aforeſaid, ſhall be deemed, taken, adjudged, and expounded to be good and available in the Law to all intents and purpoſes whatſoever, and ſhall be accounted as good Records as this Book it ſelf hereunto annexed; Any Law or Cuſtome to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That this Act or any thing therein contained, ſhall not be prejudicial or hurtfull unto the Kings Profeſſor of the Law with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Vniverſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> for or concerning the Prebend of
<hi>Shipton,</hi> within the Cathedral Church of <hi>Sarum,</hi> united and annexed unto the place of the ſame Kings Profeſſor for the time being, by the late King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, That whereas the ſix and thirtieth Article of the Nine and thirty Articles agreed upon by the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of both Provinces, and the whole Clergy in the Convocation holden at
<hi>London,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thouſand five hundred ſixty two, for the avoiding of diverſities of Opinions, and for eſtabliſhing of conſent, touching true Religion, is in theſe words following,
<hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">That the Book of Conſecration of Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining of Prieſts and Deacons, lately ſet forth in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and confirmed at the ſame time by Authority of Parliament, doth contain all things neceſſary to ſuch Conſecration and Ordaining, neither hath it any thing that of it ſelf is ſuperſtitious and ungodly; And therefore whoſoever are Conſecrated or Ordered according to the Rites of<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46974:9"/>that Book, ſince the ſecond year of the aforenamed King <hi>Edward</hi> unto this time, or hereafter ſhall be Conſecrated or Ordered according to the ſame Rites; We decree all ſuch to be rightly, orderly and lawfully Conſecrated and Ordered;</q>
            <p>It be enacted, And be it therefore Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That all Subſcriptions hereafter to be had or made unto the ſaid Articles, by any Deacon, Prieſt or Eccleſiaſticall perſon or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever, who by this Act or any other Law now in force is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſubſcribe unto the ſaid Articles, ſhall be conſtrued and taken to extend, and ſhall be applied (for and touching the ſaid ſix and thirtieth Article) unto the Book containing the form and manner of Making, Ordaining and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons in this Act mentioned, in ſuch ſort and manner as the ſame did heretofore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto the Book ſet forth in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, mentioned in the ſaid ſix and thirtieth Article, Any thing in the ſaid Article, or in any Statute, Act or Canon heretofore had or made, to the contrary thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That the Book of Common Prayer and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments and other Rites and Ceremonies of this Church of <hi>England,</hi> together with the form and manner of Ordaining, and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons heretofore in uſe, and reſpectively eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament in the firſt and eighth years of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſhall be ſtill uſed and obſerved in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> untill the Feaſt of St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord God, One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and two.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by His MAJESTIES Printers, and Re-printed at <hi>Edinburgh, Anno Dom.</hi> 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46974:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
